Finding Aid for Camilla and Ethel Green Family Papers, 1827-1988
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
Camilla and Ethel Green Family Papers 1827-1988, 1910-1955
Green family.
1 oversize folder
8.0 linear feet
98117 Aa 2 UAm
Camilla and Ethel Green were mother and daughter who resided in the Ann Arbor, Michigan area from the late 1800s through their deaths in 1955 and 1988, respectively. Both women corresponded prolifically with their family, friends and former students. This collection consists primarily of their letters, which are largely organized chronologically if not already grouped by correspondent.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
The papers were donated by the Ethel Green estate through the Russell Bidlack estate (donor no. 3966 ) on June 24, 2004.
The collection is open to research.
Camilla Blanche Gillett was born on April 11, 1870 and married Frank Albert Green on December 19, 1886. The couple divorced in 1893 with one daughter, Ethel Margaret Green, born on October 25, 1889. Mother and daughter continued to live primarily in the Ann Arbor, Michigan area and remained extremely close during their lifetimes. Note that Camilla is sometimes referred to as "Millie Gillett", and she will frequently sign her letters "Kim", especially when sent to Ethel. Ethel is occasionally referred to by her middle name, Margaret.
Camilla served as the Secretary of the Department of Engineering at the University of Michigan from 1907 to 1942. In that time, she helped to establish the Business and Professional Women's Society and played an active role helping students, especially the female engineers. As a result, Camilla became a mother-figure to them, so much that many came to address her as "Mother", "Mama" and other salutations of endearment. Select students were among the more frequent correspondents with both Camilla and Ethel. In addition, during the 1930s, Camilla aided then-retired Dean Mortimer Cooley in a compilation of the history of the University of Michigan.
Ethel spent some time as a teacher, but also traveled and stayed with friends and relatives in and around Michigan. Late in her life, Ethel befriended Russell and Melva Bidlack, a former professor who served as the first Dean of the University of Michigan School of Information (then called the School of Library Science). Upon Ethel's death, this collection of papers was bequeathed to Russell Bidlack with the recommendation that they be donated to the Michigan Historical Collections at the Bentley Historical Library.
Both Camilla and Ethel were beloved members of their community. However, both suffered frequent illnesses during their lifetime. Camilla eventually passed away after one of these sicknesses in 1955. Ethel lived on for another 32 years until she died in 1988.
This collection reflects the papers amassed by Camilla and Ethel Green over nearly a century. It is divided into four series: Family Background and Documents, University of Michigan, Correspondence, Photographs. The bulk of the collection occurs from 1910 to 1955 and features correspondence with various friends and family members; a large portion of the letters has been organized by correspondent and/or the correspondent's family, and the remainder is sorted chronologically.
Subjects:
Green, Camilla B., 1870-1955.; Bird, James Pyper.; Cheever, Byron William, 1841-1888.; Butts, William Henry.; Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; Wood, De Volson, 1832-1897.; Green family.; Green, Ethel.
Subjects - Visual Materials:
Angell, James Burrill, 1829-1916.; Ann Arbor High School (Mich.). Class of 1885.; Butts, William Henry.; Camp Davis (University of Michigan); Cooley, Mortimer E. (Mortimer Elwyn), 1855-1944.; Davis, Joseph Baker, 1845-1920.; Green, Camilla B., 1870-1955.; Green family.; Green, Ethel.; Mooreville (Mich.); University of Michigan. College of Engineering.; University of Michigan. Homoeopathic Hospital.; West Engineering Building (University of Michigan); Women--Michigan--Ann Arbor.
Contributors:
Green, Camilla B., 1870-1955.; Green, Ethel.
Genre Terms:
Photographs.
- Family Background and Documents
  The Family Background and Documents series (1.5 linear feet, 1836-1988) contains biographical information for not only Camilla and Ethel Green, but also their family as a whole. A narrative history of the Gillett family (Camilla's paternal side), marriage into the Bowers family (Camilla's maternal side), and their activities is included alongside legal documents, such as contracts, certifications and wills. Genealogical information in the form of family trees and birth and death records has been isolated in two folders, and further information can be found by perusing Camilla's notebooks and the "Addresses and Information" folder. These notebooks, scrapbooks and diaries help to supplement and contextualize the events discussed in correspondence with colleagues, friends and family.
  - Biographical Information (Box 1)
    (include Camilla Green family and autobiographical notes)
  - Family Trees (Box 1)
  - Birth and Death Records (Box 1)
  - Deeds and Contracts 1836-1954 (Box 1)
  - First Baptist Church 1860-1954 (Box 1)
  - John Gillett's Daybook 1863 (Box 1)
  - Mary J. Gillett's Health 1912-1913 (Box 1)
  - Wills 1890-1910 (Box 1)
  - Cemetery Arrangements 1911-1947 (Box 1)
  - Camilla Green
    - Scrapbook 1883 (Box 1)
    - Marriage and Divorce 1886-1892, 1896 (Box 1)
    - "Papa's Wee Girl" Copyright 1889 (Box 1)
    - Letters of Recommendation 1892-1904 (Box 1)
    - Notary Public Certification 1896-1926 (Box 1)
    - Notebooks and Ledgers 1897-1950 (Box 1)
    - Memberships 1901-1955 (Box 1)
    - T-Square Society 1915-1920 (Box 1)
    - Official Papers 1917-1943 (Box 1)
    - Health Records 1920-1948 (Box 1)
    - Wills and Obituaries 1920-1955, 1956-1957 (Box 1)
    - Diaries 1938-1955, 4 volumes (Box 1)
    - Articles 1923-1954 (Box 1)
    - Addresses and Information (Box 1)
    - Recipes (Box 1)
    - Writing (Box 1)
    - Notes and Miscellaneous Information (Box 1)
  - Ethel Green
    - Birth Certificate 1889, 1953 (Box 1)
    - Baptism 1904, 1965 (Box 1)
    - Diaries 1905-1909, 1945, 6 volumes (Box 1)
    - Education 1897-1910 (Box 1)
    - Schoolwork (Box 2)
    - Notebooks and Ledgers 1910-1973 (Box 2)
    - Hillsdale Public Schools 1912-1914 (Box 2)
    - San Juan, Porto Rico 1919-1920 (Box 2)
    - Women's Club 1920-1951 (Box 2)
    - University of Michigan 1932 (Box 2)
    - Official Papers 1937-1978 (Box 2)
    - Miscellaneous Records 1885-1958 (Box 2)
    - Power of Attorney 1977-1982 (Box 2)
    - Estate Management 1982-1988 (Box 2)
    - Wills 1918-1988 (Box 2)
    - Preliminary Inventory of Possessions 1988 (Box 2)
    - Inventory of Possessions 1988 (Box 2)
    - Memorial Service 1988 (Box 2)
    - Letters Regarding Her Death
      - Sent 1988 (Box 2)
      - Not Sent 1988 (Box 2)
    - Writing (Box 2)
  - Miscellaneous Writing (Box 2)
- University of Michigan (Camilla)
  The University of Michigan series (1.0 linear feet, 1906-1961) documents Camilla's employment with the Department of Engineering. Her increase in responsibilities over 35 years in the Secretary's office is portrayed in the "Personnel Records" folder, while daily activities can be chronicled in her notebooks and professional correspondence. In addition, she remained in touch with a number of former students; letters containing primarily pleasantries and personal updates for the department have been included in this series. However, Camilla also grew quite close to many former students; those letters are included among the larger, personal Correspondence series. Select photographs might be found in these correspondence folders, as well as in the Faculty and Administrators folders.
  - Salary Records 1906-1942 (Box 2)
  - Personnel Records 1911-1941 (Box 2)
  - Notebooks 1909-1932 (Box 2)
  - Retirement
    - Pension 1935-1947 (Box 2)
    - Celebration 1942 (Box 2)
  - Athletics 1909-1942 (Box 2)
  - Centennial Engineering Celebration 1953 (Box 2)
  - Events 1929-1947 (Box 2)
  - Homeopathy 1884-1935 (Box 2)
  - Official Documents 1909-1932 (Box 2)
  - Research on History (Box 2)
  - Faculty and Administrators
    - James Burrill Angell 1912-1927 (Box 2)
    - James Pyper Bird 1906-1947 (Box 2)
    - William Henry Butts 1936-1946 (Box 2)
    - Byron William Cheever 1937 (Box 2)
    - Mortimer E. Cooley 1936-1937 (Box 2)
    - Members of the Faculties 1841-1912 (Box 2)
    - DeVolson Wood 1886-1896 (Box 3)
    - Belle Wood Hammond 1936-1953 (Box 3)
  - Student Affairs
    - Alumni: Engineering Class of 1912, 1942-1952 (Box 3)
    - Chinese Students 1922-1935 (Box 3)
    - Fancy Dress Party 1916 (Box 3)
    - Women Students 1911-1950 (Box 3)
    - Business and Professional Women's Club 1921-1961 (Box 3)
  - Professional Correspondence
    - Interdepartmental 1916-1941 (Box 3)
    - Suggestions for Improvements 1916-1937 (Box 3)
    - Assistance 1924-1946 (Box 3)
    - Mortimer Cooley 1911-1944 (Box 3)
    - Harry H. Steinhauser Jr. 1937-1942 (Box 3)
  - Correspondence with Former Students
    - Giang Ai Lan Kiang 1926-1942 (Box 3)
    - Kuan Shih Yuan-Wu 1933-1946 (Box 3)
    - 1911-1915 (Box 3)
    - 1916-1920 (Box 3)
    - 1921-1929 (Box 3)
    - 1930-1952 (Box 3)
- Correspondence
  The Correspondence series (5.5 linear feet, 1827-1988) contains letters to and from the Gillett/Bowers/Green families over 161 years. The Bowers folder features letters among Camilla's maternal relatives prior to Mary Juliette's marriage to John Oscar Gillett in 1869. The Gillett/Bowers folder contains letters, primarily from Camilla's grandparents, Jonathan and Harriet Bowers, to both Mary and her sister, Minercy (later married to James Fisher). In letters to her granddaughter, Ethel Green, Mary J. Gillett often signed them "Baba".
  A significant portion of the Correspondence series is organized by sender. These letters may be addressed to either Camilla or Ethel, though most of them are to Camilla. Many folders also contain letters from various family members, and these have been grouped by clan (e.g. the Bird Family). Among the correspondents are family members (e.g. Ethel's cousin Vera) and Camilla's former students (e.g. Dottie Macomber).
  Those letters not separated by sender have been arranged chronologically according to the addressed recipient. Note that many letters sent to Camilla also feature greetings to Ethel, while a few instances generate individual letters to each woman from a single correspondent. The holiday and birthday cards represent a selection of greetings received for that occasion. The "Drafts and Notes" and "Undated" folders contain letters over a wide time-span and include drafts of responses to letters, notes made by Camilla or Ethel, and correspondence to various family members.
  - Family
    - Bowers 1827-1849 (Box 3)
    - Gillett/Bowers 1867-1896 (Box 3)
    - To Minercy Fisher 1866-1929 (Box 3)
    - To Mary Gillett 1889-1912 (Box 3)
    - Undated, probably to Mary Gillett (Box 3)
    - From Mary J. Gillett ("Baba") to Ethel Green 1910-1912 (Box 3)
    - Between Camilla and Ethel Green 1901-1913 (Box 3)
    - Between Camilla and Ethel Green 1913-1942 (Box 4)
  - By Sender
    - Cynthia Allen 1973-1988 (Box 4)
    - Bidlack Family 1960-1988 (Box 4)
    - Ethel Green to Bidlack Family 1981-1988 (Box 4)
    - Bird Family 1907-1955 (Box 4)
    - Hugh Brodie 1918-1930 (Box 4)
    - Hobart Calkins 1912-1957 (Box 4)
    - Belle Castle 1923-1953 (Box 4)
    - Vera and Clarke Family to Camilla Green 1924-1955 (Box 4)
    - Vera and Clarke Family to Ethel Green 1912-1982 (Box 4)
    - Alice Clement 1908-1910 (Box 4)
    - Collins Family 1917-1955 (Box 5)
    - William G. Cushman Jr. 1910-1912 (Box 5)
    - Delaney Family 1971-1983 (Box 5)
    - Thomas J. Doran 1913-1919 (Box 5)
    - Gibbs Family 1919-1950 (Box 5)
    - Clara Ford 1972-1979 (Box 5)
    - Ai Lau 1921-1932 (Box 5)
    - Grace and Winfield Line 1924-1946 (Box 5)
    - Dottie Macomber 1925-1939 (Box 5)
    - Dottie Macomber 1940-1955 (Box 5)
    - Mok Family 1939-1953 (Box 5)
    - Grace Powers 1910-1948 (Box 6)
    - Julie N. Sale 1907-1926 (Box 6)
    - Jeanne Solis 1933-1943 (Box 6)
    - Luella Whitmore 1933-1955 (Box 6)
  - To Camilla Green
    - Pre-1900 (Box 6)
    - 1900-1910 (Box 6)
    - 1911-1920 (Box 6)
    - 1921-1925 (Box 6)
    - 1926-1942, 17 folders (Box 6)
    - 1943-1955, 13 folders (Box 7)
  - To Ethel Green
    - To 1910 (Box 7)
    - 1911-1920 (Box 7)
    - 1921-1930 (Box 7)
    - 1931-1940 (Box 7)
    - 1941-1950 (Box 7)
    - 1951-1954 (Box 7)
    - 1955 Sympathy (Box 7)
    - 1956-1960 (Box 7)
    - 1961-1970 (Box 7)
    - 1971-1976 (Box 7)
    - 1977-1980 (Box 8)
    - 1981-1988 (Box 8)
  - Undated (Box 8)
- Photographs
  The Photographs series (1.0 linear feet, 1871-1978) primarily features portraits of friends and relatives. Similar to the Correspondence series, Photographs have been grouped by families when possible, and are otherwise alphabetized if the subject has been identified. Following the images of individuals, photographs have been included of specific locations, most notably the University of Michigan alumni, administrators and buildings.
  - Camilla Green 1871-1931 (Box 8)
  - Ethel Green 1890-1985 (Box 8)
  - Camilla and Ethel Green 1899-1931 (Box 8)
  - Camilla and Ethel's Homes 1933-1978 (Box 8)
  - Family
    - Bowers (Box 8)
    - Fishers (Box 8)
    - Gilletts (Box 8)
    - Greens (Box 8)
    - Wheelers (Box 8)
  - Baier Family (Box 8)
  - Bird Family (Box 8)
  - Clark Family (Box 8)
  - Close Family (Box 8)
  - Collins Family (Box 8)
  - DeForest Family (Box 8)
  - Danny and David Dow (Box 8)
  - Gibbs Family (Box 8)
  - Allan Handly (Box 8)
  - Lewis Family (Box 8)
  - Grace and Winfield Line (Box 8)
  - Mok Family (Box 8)
  - Portraits
    - A-C (Box 8)
    - D-M (Box 8)
    - P-Z (Box 8)
    - Groups (Box 8)
    - Unlabeled (Box 8)
  - Ann Arbor (Box 8)
  - Baptist Church (Box 8)
  - Mooreville (Box 8)
  - University of Michigan
    - Alumni (Box 8)
    - Alumni Engineering Class of 1912, 1942 (Box 8)
    - Administrators (Box 8)
    - Hugh Brodie (Box 8)
    - Mortimer E. Cooley (Box 8)
    - Thomas J. Doran (Box 8)
    - Group Portraits (Box 8)
    - Camp Davis (Box 8)
    - Campus Buildings
      - Images (Box 8)
      - Negatives (Box 8)
    - Homeopathic Hospital
      - Buildings (Box 8)
      - Faculty and Staff 1881-1885 (Box 8)
    - Women's Groups (Box 8)